so we're gonna play a 20 minute game
it's gonna be 10 to minute moves and to
manage the amount of information that is
gonna be flowing inside of that space
we're gonna be using notes so as we're
listening to each other we're going to
be noting down various components of the
conversation so we can try and get as
many integration points as possible
without losing some of the richness
which is just flowing by
[Music]
in a decaying society art if it is to be
truthful must reflect that decay unless
it is to abandon its social function art
must portray the world as changeable and
seek to change it that's those are not
words get from here these are this is
this is a quote a slightly mangled one
but nevertheless raises three very
interesting notions firstly what is the
function of art in society secondly it
disconnects art from beauty I mean if if
art is to be truthful it is not
necessarily going to be beautiful and I
think in the minds of many people art
and beauty are profoundly connected to
each other and the yeah and so art has
an ability to communicate on a level
beyond and underneath language language
takes things and puts them into little
boxes and then puts those boxes in a
sequence and art is able to deliver in a
much more complete and direct way and so
the function of art in society is to do
that which the other things in society
cannot do
for example science and analysis and
logic can only work through things in a
sequential manner art and present the
whole thing at once art or artists more
specifically are an early warning system
to the decay of a society one of the
most sure signs of a flourishing society
is a burgeoning and thriving art scene
but as reflection as a reflective
surface a mirror we create putting as
much of ourselves on
to the surface so others can peer into
it and see the cosmos reflected the goal
of art to create the ultimate
masterpiece the masterpiece in which all
of being is contained in one point and
one could swallow it like a pill one
could look at it like the Gorgons gaze
and be transfigure ated instantaneously
into the full knowledge of all of being
art reveals the world as malleable can
transform matter and by transforming
matter we can transform mind we can use
language to transform Minds this linear
flow or we can also use other materials
that have a nonlinear grammar we can
create interconnections of points put
them on a canvas arrange them in the
right way arrange these different
dimensions in the right way and they
resonate together they become more than
the sum of their parts they become a
unit in and of themselves the one can
contemplate contemplate art contemplate
that various sub dimensions of the
artwork and then contemplate the whole
and flow in this back and forth process
between contemplating the part and
contemplating the totality
fractal speaking to a variety even an
infinity of scales all at once from the
micro to the macro that connection
across scale from and not just across
scale but across domain from the
microbes at the macro but from the
physical to the emotional to the
spiritual to the divine though the the
the the ability of art of art to cross
all of these things simultaneously is is
is unmatched by anything else art has
the ability the mirror thing I mean that
the mirror is a is a it's the boundary
between awareness and mystery that's
that's the mirror and so art is
navigating is the wrong word art is
mapping dif no not defining feeling
feeling what that mirror is and using
that to reveal using that to elevate
using that to redeem using that to
examine and if necessary reorder one's
perceptions of the world
you
ah brings us from one level of
resolution to another font from the
level of resolution of our of the
minutiae of our daily lives it allows us
to step out of that into a into a
grander broader perspective which then
informs again the micro but as a multi
level eye that sees at multiple levels
of resolution simultaneously zoom in
close enough and see the artistry of
each individual pigment on the canvas
zoom out far enough and see the canvas
in the context of the totality of all
being come close enough that you just
have the canvas and the frame
shifting the canvas into the frame
shifting the frame into the canvas
compressing the frame until one sees a
tiny part of the canvas increasing it
until one sees the totality of the
canvas the great canvas of being a great
mirror sometimes solid sometimes liquid
sometimes transparent to lose oneself in
a work of art to be so deeply plunged
into the work but then one forgets
oneself and one enters into connection
with the artist to see the artist beyond
the art to pass through the portal of
the work and to see the artist the
imaginations we have of the artist
who made this the knowledge we have the
artist how that transforms the artwork
the frame around the artwork how
delicately or grossly it has been carved
the invisible frames around all of our
works around all of our lives that we do
not see that we inhabit the work itself
but we forget our frames how can we
reclaim our frames frame is something
that we put around something to say this
is this is where it ends this is this is
the limits of it
[Music]
it's strange in a way that so many works
of art are put in frames because art
surely seeks to transcend the very
notion of frames
it's the definition of what art is is is
quite troublesome is art in the intent
of the person producing the art or is
the art in the thing that is produced
there is surely some both are true there
is nature capable of producing art
certainly nature is capable of producing
beauty but what what is it that art is
is it is it unique to human beings when
a beaver met with and when beavers make
a dam do they do so artistically what if
art is the art is looking in the mirror
of the mystery and finding something of
value in that which you then seek to
express to the world is that uniquely
human is is is any other creature
capable of artistic endeavor the frame
and the membrane transfer aiming process
art as skill practice process artists
communication the
says of art metabolism of art perceiving
the world inhaling the world exhaling
part of the world the research process
of art where one brings in as many
different elements as possible digests
them into a new arrangement novelty a
new arrangement that has never been seen
and in being seen for the first time
reawakens parts the veil the pattern of
dust on all things that allows us to see
again as if for the first time and then
one sees the beauty once more art as the
cure
as the wave to wash away the dust to
cleanse the doors of perception and to
see once more the world as it truly is
as even greater than any work of art a
pale imitation of the grandeur of nature
to look into the infinite mirror
the surface of the mirror quiet like a
pond
with a finger
you
art is a pale imitation of nature that's
beautiful and so art is an attempt a
humble and pointless and worthless
attempt to do what nature does all the
time the perfection that is embodied in
every aspect of nature is what arcs
spart seeks to capture and so the artist
when engaging in their art is is is that
right they they are they are directly in
touch
somehow or another with the process of
creation itself directly grounded in
being itself endeavoring with the
limitations and inadequacies that
they're saddled with to to capture that
and bring it into static being right
this is the point it's it's it's
essentially a photograph it's
endeavoring to bring into static
continuous being that which is only ever
fleeting and instantaneous in the real
world
God is it's a it's a it's an impossible
and yet heroic endeavor to seek to do
that to touch their to touch the
absolute essence of the mystery grab a
little thing of it to hold on to it well
enough the frustration of knowing what
it is that you've brought back with you
and and the impossibility of ever really
expressing that fully must be depressing
at times
capture a grain of dust and shine it in
the light
static art dynamic art moving images and
static images and yet even the longest
movie ever is static in comparison with
the dynamic nature of nature art as a
sacred ritual of recreation over
recreating the cosmos in a micro cosmos
games as art games as art with many
moving pieces games as the artistic
arrangement of systems
that reflect
interrelations of nature how can we
create games that reflect our
relationships between each other between
ourselves and the cosmos how can we
summon the cosmos down onto earth in the
forms of sacred games
you
to manifest a work of art
to concentrate to pay attention to that
tiny mote of dust that we hold for one
moment in our fingers to shine it under
all spectra of light and darkness so we
can make it blossom games as arts as The
Artful playing of games as the artful
design of games which then by being
artfully played reinforce the artfulness
of the designer in the first place
life itself as our this is a
long-standing notion of interest the the
honing of your presence or one's
presence in the moment to the point
where everything one does one does as
though it were a work of art it's
finding that balance and harmony and
connection to and finding peace in the
doing of the thing that you're doing it
beautifully or designing it elegantly
you're balancing it gracefully that
these these things being incorporated
into every moment of one's life
everybody has that capacity to be an
artist even if they are not producing
things which others admire the notion of
artistry is something which can be
directly lived and experienced the way
one strokes a cat understanding the
nature of the cat and and the incredibly
subtle feelings and interactions between
the fur and the hand understanding what
the cat enjoys and doesn't enjoy exactly
what he said this is a this is a form of
artfulness it's a complete presence of
understanding of attunement to Joy in
love of the moment the art of building
and breaking symmetry of building
greater and greater symmetries and
breaking greater and greater symmetries
of nesting symmetries within broken
symmetries within symmetries creating
dynamic symmetries between oneself and
the world the grip the dynamic symmetry
between fingers and the thumb and the
thing which has gripped the point of
attention the tension in the mind the
modulation of the tension in the mind to
grip perfectly that mote of the universe
that specific thought of the universe
and then to draw a line between two dots
and one more and to draw a shape and
then one more a horizon
another shape of star
a feeling a memory
so many different dimensions of the same
thing
put together in a frame where the
interrelationships bubble
now this one comes to the surface then
this one then this one then this one and
then you can see all of the waves being
created simultaneously this great waving
mirror and then silence one more
flatness
take it in
let it go
you